Guide to the Mary Coolidge Rentschler Collection 1793-2000 (bulk, 1875-1950) MS 2999
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Manuscripts and memorabilia
  - Subseries I.B. Mary Coolidge Rentschler (1892–1988) [MCR]
    - Correspondence, 1933 March-1940 March (Offsite-box Man-10, Folder 12)
      Correspondence from Katherine W. Atkins in USA and Cuba to Mary C. Rentschler. Family/community news; USA: amateur dramatics, local bank closure, Hitler on radio. Cuba: schooling for poor children, WWII. Llewellyn Hughes in Cuba, economic hardship, very poor crop.
    - Correspondence, circa 1934-1946 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 1)
      Miscellaneous correspondence from Mary C. Rentschler in Massachusetts, Georgia, and new YOrk, to Gordon S. Rentschler in New York. Social engagements. Children's daily lives. Mother's failing health. Birth of George Adam Rentschler Jr. (December 2, 1937).
    - Correspondence, card, valentine, 1935 June-1938 December (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 2)
      Correspondence and cards from Faith A. Witter, Phoebe R. Stanton, Mary R. Lowrey, and Susan R. Witter to Mary C. Rentschler and Gordon S. Rentschler. Children's letters and handmade cards to their parents (FAR's stepfather). Letter from nanny Camilly to MCR.
    - Correspondence, 1935 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 3)
      Thank you letters from Wm. C. Osborn (sp?) and Henr W. Hobben (sp?) to Mary C. Rentschler.
    - Correspondence, 1936 November 25 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 4)
      Letter from David H. Coolidge to Mary C. Rentschler. Probably DHC Jr. to his niece. Describes his trip to the South of France, accompanied by a nurse on board ship.
    - Correspondence, 1936 December 14-1954 June 11 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 5)
      Letters of interest selected by Mary C. Rentschler:
      1) A. Lawrence Lowell thanking MCR for 80th birthday wishes
      2) From Norcott re: engagement in Cuba
      3) Condolences to widow of Harvey S. Firestone Jr.
      4) Thank you from British Queen re: gift
    - Correspondence, 1937 September 25-1943 March 2 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 6)
      Social correspondence mainly from Isabel Coolidge and Charles A. Coolidge Jr. IC re: family news; attitudes of the younger gengeration to war (June 25, 1941). CAC and Julia C. Deane re: storm damage at Marion (September 1938).
    - Correspondence, 1938 February 4 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 7)
      Letter from Josephine H. Kenyon, M.D., to Mary C. Rentschler. Medical report to MCR, recommending thyroid and intestinal medication as well as exercise and painting.
    - Correspondence, 1938 June 10-1941 January 2 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 8)
      Correspondence from Helen R. Waldon and Sidney D. Waldon to Mary C. Rentschler & Gordon S. Rentschler: Rentschler girls on vacation in Michigan. Wing Lakers parties. Detroit subway construction bid by SDW. Joy at Republican victories, upset at Roosevelt re-election.
    - Correspondence, 1938 June 27-August 21 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 9)
      Correspondence from Faith A. Witter to Mary C. Rentschler, Gordon S. Rentschler, Helen R. Waldon, and Sidney D. Waldon. FAW at Diamond Ranch, Wyoming. Wonderful descriptions of young elite on holiday: escapades in an exquisite setting.
    - Correspondence, 1939 January 31-December 4 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 10)
      Correspondence mainly from Julia C. Deane to her sister, Mary C. Rentschler. Also letters from Frederick Deane and Julia c. Crowley. Family news, domestic life: children, health, thankyous for gifts, MCR moving to E. 72nd St. from 933 5th Ave.
    - Correspondence, card, valentine, 1939 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 11)
      Correspondence from Phoebe R. Stanton, Mary R. Lowrey, Susan R. Witter, Agnes Campbell "Camilly" to Mary C. Rentschler, Gordon S. Rentschler, and Faith A. Witter. Letters and greeting cards from home, school, and vacation. Letters from the nanny to MCR and GSR.
    - Correspondence, card, valentine, 1940-1947 (Offsite-box Man-11, Folder 12)
      Correspondence from Phoebe R. Stanton, Mary C. Lowrey, Susan R. Witter, Faith A. Witter, and Mary Boyer to Mary C. Rentschler and Gordon S. Rentschler. Letters and cards to the parents, including holiday adventures at ranch in Wyoming, with staff reports on the children.
    - Correspondence, 1940 January 17-December 29 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 1)
      Correspondence mainly from Julia C. Deane to Mary C. Rentschler. Family news: her children & MCR's children, social events. 81st birthday party of Katherine W. Atkins. Isabel Coolidge financial situation. Camilly's letter re: children in fancy dress in Michigan (July 9).
    - Correspondence, 1940 May 4-1941 October 26 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 2)
      Correspondence from Katherine W. Atkins to Mary C. Rentschler from Massachusetts & Cuba beginning of WWII. Massachusetts: strep throat, shipment of British children. Cuba: wedding, sickness, Marciol [Martial] Facio decorating a dead man, cultural attitudes vis-a-vis British.
    - Correspondence, 1940 August 9 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 3)
      Letter from John F. Neylan to Mary C. Rentschler, humourously encouraging Gordon S. Rentschler to take a vacation from work and visit him and his family in San Francisco and on their ranch.
    - Correspondence, 1941 January 30-1942 April 2 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 4)
      Correspondence from Julia C. Deane in Massachusetts to Mary C. Rentschler in Ohio and New York. Social correspondence and thankyou letters. Children's lives, including coming out parties. MCR and GSR funded parties.
    - Correspondence, 1942 March-April (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 5)
      Correspondence from Katherine W. Atkins in Cienfuegos, Cuba, to Mary C. Rentschler in New York. Social life in WWII Cuba. Frequent mention of daughter Helen Atkins and son-in-law William Claflin.
    - Correspondence, 1942 March 6-29 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 6)
      Miscellaneous correspondence to Mary C. Rentschler in New York from family members at the time of her hysterectomy. Letters from Charles A. Coolidge Jr., Mary C. Lowrey, Phoebe R. Stanton, Susan R. Witter, Helen R. Waldon, Helen A. Claflin, Louise M. Mills.
    - Correspondence, circa 1942 April-1943 March (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 7)
      Correspondence from Katherine W. Atkins in Belmont, Massachusetts to Mary C. Rentschler in Locust Valey, New York. Social life of upper-class woman during WWII. Red Cross work, fund raisers, political opinions of KWA. News of daughter Helen and son-in-law William Claflin.
    - Correspondence, 1942 June 7-1947 April 6 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 8)
      Correspondence from Helen R. Waldon in Ohio to Mary C. Rentschler in New York. Social news and life in Ohio, including Wing Laker group gatherings.
    - Correspondence, 1943 January 26 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 9)
      Letter from C. Scott White (artist) to Mary C. Rentschler re: commission of a pastel drawing for her brother, Charles A. Coolidge Jr. [This letter was removed from the painting by Susan R. Witter and transferred to the present collection in April 2000.]
    - Correspondence, 1945 January 30-March 13 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 10)
      Correspondence from Mary C. Rentschler & Helen R. Waldon in Hamilton, Ohio, to Gordon S. Rentschler in New York. Correspondence from MCR in Ohio after death of Sidney D. Waldon. Emotional crisis of HRW. Illegitimate children? (February 2, 1945). Susan R. Witter at Chapin (January 1945).
    - Correspondence, circa 1945-1950 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 11)
      Miscellaneous social correspondence between Mary C. Rentschler, Faith A. Witter, and Katherine W. Atkins, mainly Locust Valley, Long Island (also Bay Shore, New York, and Cuba).
    - Correspondence, publication, circa 1945-1952 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 12)
      Book: "Tell the People: Talks with James Yen About the Mass Education Movement" by Pearl S. Buck. And letter by the author soliciting Mary C. Rentschler to help finance the American Chinese Committee of the Mass Education Movement.
    - Correspondence, circa post-1946? (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 13)
      Letter from Faith A. Witter to Mary C. Rentschler, post-1946. This torn piece of a letter describes the enormous regard she has for her husband, Dean Witter, explaining that marrying him was the best thing she ever did.
    - Correspondence, news clippings, 1948 April 3-1956 May 15 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 14)
      Correspondence and news clipping re: Frederick B. Rentschler:
      1) RBR election to Board of Directors of NCB in honor of GSR
      2) Award citation for service in aeronautics industry
      3) Reminiscences, including GSR testifying in 1930s; WWII aero engines
      4) Eisenhowever condolence letter
    - Correspondence, circa 1948-1956 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 15)
      1) Annotated business card from Bernard M. Baruch to Mary C. Rentschler and gordon S. Rentschler
      2) Letter from Bernard M. Baruch to Mary C. Rentschler congratulating her on the announcement of Susan R. Witter's marriage
    - Correspondence, 1949 April 10 (Offsite-box Man-12, Folder 16)
      Letter from Winston Churchill's private secretary, Elizabeth Gilliatt, in London, UK, thanking Mary C. Rentschler for cigars.
    - Correspondence, 1951 March 8 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 1)
      Letter from Amon G. Carter to Mary C. Rentschler re: gift of steak from a champion steer.
    - Correspondence, 1953 June 13 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 2)
      Letter from Edith Dent to Mary C. Rentschler requesting membership to Colony Club for friend Mrs. E. Cuyler Hammond.
    - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 3)
      Miscellaneous items, including:
      1) letter from J. C. Penney to Mary C. Rentschler, thanking her for social engagement. Penney sending MCR a copy of his autobiography and other books
      2) copy of Gettysburg address
      3) humorous statistic of U.S. (non) working population
    - Correspondence, 1958 February 13 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 4)
      Letter from Helen A. Claflin in Cuba to Mary C. Rentschler (probably in New York or Massachusetts). Daily life in Cuba: poor crop, sickness, dangers of childbirth.
    - Correspondence, 1974 January 16 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 5)
      Memorandum and notes re: porphyria (blood disease). MCR writes that the disease is carried in the Shepley bloodline.
    - Revolutionary War uniform decorations, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-12)
      "US army uniform decoration. Inherited through CAC Sr., who got them in a collection of 'curios' inherited from his stepfather Francis (last name) or from his own father DHC, depending on date used." [Medal from Order of the Cincinnati?] Undated, but commemorates the 1776 Revolutionary War.
    - Miscellaneous: Diary, correspondence, 1811-1821, 1980 November 16-21 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 6)
      Travel diary of Benjamin Clapp, 1811-1821 (great-grandfather of Mary C. Rentschler); Biography of Benjamin Clapp and correspondence between Mary C. Rentschler and Hayden shepley, 1980 (great-great-grandson of Benjamin Clapp?).
    - Benjamin Clapp miniatures and wedding ring, 1823 February 15 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-13)
      Wedding ring of Benjamin Clapp and Mary C. Behn, February 15, 1823. (From either New York, N.Y., or St. Louis, Missouri?) Also, miniature portraits (paintings?) of Benjamin Clapp and Mary C. Behn in separate lockets with hair braid in a recess in the back mourning hair?), circa 1823?
    - Misc. loose maps, 1839-1964 (Offsite-box Ovz-3)
      1) Manhattan, New York (1839, copy?)
      2) Cape Cod, Massachusetts (undated?)
      3) Rogue River, Oregon (1964)
    - Miscellaneous: Correspondence, 1857 May 23 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 7)
      Copy of a letter from Lord Macauley in UK to H. E. Randall in New York. Anti-Jeffersonian text detailing danger to liberty and civilization of a strictly democratic society.
    - Mary C. Rentschler brass [bronze?] baby shoes, 1892 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-15)
      Brass? mould of Mary C. Rentschler's baby shoes.
    - Miscellaneous: Drawing, correspondence, 1906-1936 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 8)
      Drawing by Mary C. Rentschler (1906). Accompanied by a letter (1936) from Charles A. Coolidge Jr. to Gordon S. Rentschler, explaining that he found the image among his father's possessions.
    - Julia S. Coolidge genealogy, circa 1907 (Offsite-box Mem-17)
      Genealogy of the Shepley, Coolidge, Clapp, Wyeth, Hill, Walker, Behn, Shurtleff, Cushman, Atwood, Shaw, Carleton, Gibson, and Goss families.
    - Miscellaneous: News clipping, circa 1910/1911 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 9)
      Press clipping re: debutante ball for Mary C. Rentschler at Copley Hall, Boston, Massachusetts. Mentions Mrs. Winston Churchill.
    - Miscellaneous: Cooking recipes, circa 1910-? (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 10)
      Miscellaneous loose cooking recipes belonging to Mary C. Rentschler.
    - Mary C. Rentschler cooking recipes, circa 1916-1965 (Offsite-box 2, Box Mem-20)
      Bound volume, alphabeticaly indexed, of cooking recipes collected by Mary C. Rentschler.
    - Edward Ayer travel reminiscences, circa 1918? (Offsite-box 2, Box Mem-21)
      Gift to Charles A. Coolidge Sr. of a travel log by Edward E. Ayer describing his journeys around the globe, 1860-1918 (many by automobile).
    - Miscellaneous: Notebooks, 1923-1932 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 11)
      Notebooks of Mary C. Rentschler listing Christmas gifts given and gifts to send.
    - Miscellaneous: Diary / notebook, circa 1924- (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 12)
      Diary used as record of birth dates. The diary is from 1924 with G. S. Rentschler embossed on the front, however, the handwriting inside is Mary C. Rentschler's.
    - Miscellaneous: Drawing / portrait, 1925 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 13)
      Pencil drawing of head of Mary C. Rentschler (in Havana, Cuba).
    - Miscellaneous: Scrapbook (photographs), 1931 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 14)
      Photographic scrapbook of the rules and regulations of the Meadow Island Yacht Club, Marion, Massachusetts. (Shepley family offspring.)
    - Miscellaneous: Gardening log, 1931-1939 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 15)
      Notebook and correspondence of Mary C. Rentschler concerning her garden at Locust Valley, Long Island. Includes lists of seed and bulb purchases, and color schemes for plant beds.
    - Miscellaneous: Bound volume of verse, circa 1933-1935? (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 16)
      Bound volume of "Rhymes For my Grandchildren" by Julia S. Shepley. Annotated as follows: "To my daughter Mary and to her daughters Faith, Phoebe, Mary, Susan from Julia Shepley Coolidge."
    - Miscellaneous: Membership card, 1934 March 27 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 17)
      Membership card of Mary C. Rentschler to the National Society of Colonial Dames of America in Massachusetts.
    - Mary C. Rentschler Women's City Club Cookbook, 1935 (Offsite-box 2, Box Mem-23)
      Spiral bound volume of the Women's City Club Cook Book, Detroit, Michigan.
    - Miscellaneous: Servant list, 1937 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 18)
      List of servants at the home of Mary C. Rentschler and Gordon S. Rentschler in Locust Valley, Long Island. (Some of these servants date to 1926, pre-MCR and GSR marriage; were they MCR's servants?).
    - New York World's Fair catalog, 1940 (Offsite-box 2, Box Mem-24)
      Masterpieces of Art catalogue from an exhibition at the New York World's Fair, 1940, in which the Rentschlers' lent an artwork. Letter from Waegen thanking them for their donation.
    - Miscellaneous: Gardening log, circa 1940-1945 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 19)
      Loose pages of a gardening log kept by Mary C. Rentschler for her Locust Valley, Long Island, garden. Includes lists of purchases for flower and vegetable plantings; also a Victory Garden plan.
    - Mary C. Rentschler Book of Common Prayer (bible), 1944 Christmas (Offsite-box 2, Box Mem-25)
      Bible. Book of Common Prayer from Gordon S. Rentschler, Faith A. Witter, Phoebe R. Stanton, Mary R. Lowrey, and Susan R. Witter to Mary C. Rentschler.
    - Miscellaneous: Certificate, 1945 December 6 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 20)
      Certificate from the American National Red Cross to Mary C. Rentschler for her WWII work.
    - Mary C. Rentschler keys, circa 1880-1950? (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-14)
      Small keys belonging to Mary C. Rentschler? Undated, but anywhere from 1880 to 1950?
    - Mary C. Rentschler "Treasures" wooden box, circa 1950s? (Offsite-box 3, Box Mem-26)
      Wood box, "Treasures" painted on lid. Box has children's photographs attached to the inside of the lid. The box contains a (Parisian?) wallet with "filigree" type decoration. (Is the wallet much older than the box?)
    - Miscellaneous: Publication, 1976 November-December (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 21)
      Copies of Angler magazine article "Mary Rentschler: A Blue Ribbon Fishing Partner" by Dan Abrams.
    - Miscellaneous: Publication, 1979 (Offsite-box Man-13, Folder 22)
      Copy of an article in Town and Country magazine by John Heminway re: Mary C. Rentschler and angling.
    - Genealogy / History: Atkins family (18th century), undated (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 1)
      News clipping re: larceny by Manuel Alvero, an employee of E. F. Atkins.
    - Genealogy / History: Carleton & Shurtleff, 1919 (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 2)
      Correspondence and genealogical lists.
    - Genealogy / History: Claflin, William III, 1980 February 6 (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 3)
      Obituary.
    - Blueprint: plan of land in Marion, Massachusetts, 1954 August (Offsite-box Ovz-3)
      Plan of land in Marion, Massachusetts. Coolidge family property.
    - Genealogy / History: Coolidge, Charles A. Jr., 1999 December 6 (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 4)
    - Genealogy / History: Coolidge, Charles A. Sr., 1936 April 2-3 (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 5)
      Obituaries.
    - Genealogy / History: Coolidge, Charles A. Sr., 1936, 1972, 1988 (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 6)
      Lists, publications, and articles re: architectural projects involving CAC Sr.
    - Genealogy / History: Coolidge, Charles A. Sr., 1951 Summer (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 7)
      Publication, "The American Society Legion of Honor Magazine," with a tribute to CAC Sr.
    - Genealogy / History: Coolidge & Rouse, circa 1770-1860 (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 8)
      Front page of the "Family bible of Jonas & Sarah Coolidge."
    - Genealogy / History: Coolidge / Shepley; Clapp / Behn, 1880s-1930s? (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 9)
      Genealogical materials and obituaries, including a form for entry to the Massachusetts Society of the Colonial Dames of America (for Julia S. Coolidge).
    - Genealogy / History: Nagel, Charles, 1940 January 6-7 (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 10)
    - Shepley family tree, 1855-1955 (Offsite-box Ovz-3)
    - Genealogy / History: Shepley, Mary Augusta Clapp (20th century), undated (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 11)
      Photograph of a paper written by Louise Lionberger Amory, "Reminiscences by Louise Lionberger Amory: The Love: Ama," about summer vacations in Marion, Massachusetts, at the home of matriarch Mary Augusta Clapp Shepley, a.k.a., Ama, circa 1900.
    - Genealogy / History: Shurtleff & Allerton, 1973 June 11 (Offsite-box Man-14, Folder 12)
      Correspondence and miscellaneous documents re: Shurtleff nd Allerton genealogies.
  - Subseries I.C. Gordon Sohn Rentschler (1885–1948) [GSR]
    For ease of access, business and family records of the Rentschler family from Hamilton, Ohio, were combined with Gordon S. Rentschler death paper and genealogical materials that originated in New York. However, the death papers are listed separately within Series III.
    The materials include minutes, business records, personal correspondence, certificates, diplomas, news clippings, memorabilia, photographic prints, and maps. They are a disparate body of documents, lacking in in-depth information. There is a dearth of material produced by Rentschler himself. However, when viewed in their entirety they provide a picture of a man from a successful mid-western family who entered the world of high finance and rose to the top of his profession as a result of unyielding hard work.
    The business documents include minutes of the George A. Rentschler Company from 1925–1944 (Box Man-14, Folder 13–15), as well as a letter written in 1885 concerning the company's castor patent (Box Man-14, Folder 20). The growth and scope of the Rentschler foundry is visible in a draft of the Hooven Owens Rentschler Company publication on heavy-duty engines (1919; Box Man-14, Folder 17). Product specifications, pricelists, and advertising provide useful information on production and marketing within the industry from 1923–1938 (Box 14, Folder 18). Excellent background information on the history of Butler County and Hamilton, Ohio, including the Great Flood of 1913 is found in the genealogical/historical group of documents at the end of Subseries I.C (Box Man-21, Folder 13).
    Material from the childhood and young adulthood of the Rentschler siblings consists of letters (from George to his mother), valentines (from George to his mother and Robert to his sister and brother George), essays, school reports, and yearbooks. Gordon's Hamilton High School reports and Princeton University reports (1898–1907) are found in Box Man-15, Folder 4. A train trip by Thomas A. Dorsey, Howard See, Frederick B. Rentschler, Robert P. Rentschler, and Gordon S. Rentschler to the 1904 St. Louis World's Fair provides an interesting travelogue (Box Man-15, Folder 11). The death of Robert P. Rentschler in 1915 at the age of thirty-one is recorded in a condolence letter from Louis D. Froelick, the Princeton Class Secretary, to Phoebe S. Rentschler, and in a bound resolution from his class (Box Man-15, Folder 17). The collection also contains letters from three female friends of Gordon Rentschler's: Dorothy McKinney, Antoinette C. Hearne, and Helen Marie Brant, written from 1910 to 1912 (Box Man-15, Folder 7). Brant's letters in particular contain a vivid description of a road trip across the Southwest of the United States.
    Later correspondence (circa 1918–1948) is an eclectic mix of letters recording the milestones in Rentschler's life and his personal and public service. These include: Sidney Waldon's praise for Rentschler's unsung war efforts in 1918 (Box 15, Folder 18); thankyou letters for gifts and employment assistance (Box 15, Folders 20 & 22); a tribute from his Princeton University Class of 1907, honoring his appointment as National City Bank President (Box 16, Folder 2); correspondence from James M. Cox, Governor of Ohio and 1920 presidential running mate to Franklin Delano Roosevelt, awarding him a "Rentschler Badge" for his role in breaking up a gang of horse thieves in Butler County, Ohio (1931; Box 16, Folder 7). An annotated note attached to another medal reads "struck in memory of the wash-room episode Aug 26 1933 on L.I. when some 'hero' socked the 'Kingfish'—Huey Long—in much needed retribution." Huey Long was a controversial Senator from Louisiana. The badge and the event that the note refer to are unknown. However, this was the period of banking Senate Committee Hearings in Washington, D.C. (Medal removed to Box Mem-38).